Hey, hey. What's up? What's up, my
friend? So, let me ask you, do you feel
this way? You don't know if your trading
strategy really works or not? And after
a few losing trades, you start to lose
confidence in your strategy and
sometimes even in yourself.
So, you hop from one strategy to another
with the hopes of finding something
better.
You've tried different tools, indicators
and whatnot, but the losses eventually
shows up and you don't know what to do
about it and this entire process rinse
repeat itself. Sounds familiar? And if
you can relate to it, don't worry
because in today's training you will
discover number one, my four-step
framework to create profitable trading
strategies even if you have tried
everything else and failed. I will share
with you how to get an endless supply of
trading ideas so you can develop trading
strategies that actually work. How to
create a complete trading system from
start to finish. The entries, the exits,
the setups, the risk management, so on
and so forth, so you know when exactly
to buy and sell, and you can minimize
the emotions messing with your head.
And finally, I'll give you the complete
trading rules of a trend following
system so you can profit in bull and
bare markets even during a recession. So
all this and more in today's training.
Sounds good? Then subscribe to the
channel and let's get to it.
Now the first step of the framework is
to read the right stuff. This means you
want to read trading books that contains
trading system and back tested results.
Why is that? That's because you will
then have a foundation to work with. So
you don't have to start from scratch. In
other words, you don't have to reinvent
the wheel. And another thing is that
there's a good chance these books will
contain trading systems that are likely
to work because the author's reputation
is at stake. You don't want to publish
something that doesn't work because you
know it makes your name kind of smelly,
right? So more more often than not the
systems in trading books, there's a good
chance that it will work. And if you
want to have a list of my top trading
books that contains trading systems with
back tested results, then you can
actually go to this page over here. The
URL is quite quite long. So I'll put the
link in the description below. So go to
that link, right? and you'll come to
this page and I'll send my list of top
trading books to your inbox so you can
actually know what are the trading books
worth reading and what are the which are
the ones that you don't want to waste
much time on. Yeah. So I'll put the link
in the description below. The second
part of the framework is to extract the
essence. I know that sounds kind of
complex but let me break it down. You
want to extract the essence behind a
strategy so you can actually use it to
develop your own strategy. Now you might
be thinking man Ra what do you mean by
essence? Let me explain. So if you think
about this a car an automobile what is
the essence behind a car? What are the
things that make a car a car? So if you
ask me it will be things like the
steering wheel, the engine, the body,
the chassis of a car. These are the
things the parts that make up the
essence of a car.
So what are the things that are not part
of the essence? If you ask me, it'll be
things like the air conditioner, the
windscreen. Those are, you know, nice to
have but not essential. So this is what
we mean by the essence, the core things
that make up a car. So it's the same
thing for trading. What are the essence
that is behind the strategy? So let me
give you an example. Trend following,
it's a proven strategy. When I talk
about trend following, I'm referring to
the futures trend following strategy. So
trend following does well in bull and
bare markets, especially during a
crisis, during recession when there's
fear. Why is that? Let me explain why.
Imagine you're in a cinema watching a
movie. Maybe it's Avengers Endgame,
right? And during the movie, you notice
that there's a ball of fire starting to
get bigger and bigger. And now it's at a
point where you're starting to feel the
heat starting to, you know, make you
sweat buckets. Let me ask you, will you
start to rush for the exit of the cinema
or will you continue watching the movie
till Captain America lift the hammer?
For 99.9% of you, you guys are going to
rush run for the exit because your life
comes first.
This is what we call the hurt mentality.
Now, what has this got to do with
trading?
It's the same thing. When there's fear
in the market, when there's crisis, when
there's recession, what is the herd
going to do? They will sell. They will
sell away their risky assets like
stocks. And for those who are a little
bit smarter, they will not hold in cash.
They will take that money, that capital,
and put it towards safe haven assets
like gold, bonds, US dollars, safe haven
currencies, etc. And this creates
trends, downtrend across risky assets
and uptrend in safe haven assets. And as
you know when there's trends trend
follower will profit from it. And this
is why during a crisis period during a
recession trend following does so well.
So to extract the essence you want to
ask yourself this question. What are the
concepts behind a strategy? What are the
concepts behind trend following? Well,
I'm going to share with you shortly what
are the concepts behind trend following,
plus even give you a complete trend
following system that allows you to
profit in bull and bare markets even
during a recession. But for now, let's
put that on hold and move on to the
third step of the framework, which is
turn it into an objective set of rules.
Because here's the thing, concepts, they
are vague. Like, you know, trend
following, you profit when the market is
trending. You know, you have to write
trends, but it's it's vague. How do you
turn it into a tangible set of rules?
And a simple tip that I have for you is
that you can write it in this way. If X
happens, then do Y. So for example,
let's say if you have a a red trading
day means you lost money today, right?
Then go for a walk. If you have a red
trading week, then review your trades.
And if you have a red trading month,
then start looking for a job. Yeah. So
this is how we actually turn concepts
into a tangible set of rules using the
if then uh syntax or statements how
however you want to call it. I think for
those of you who are into programming
you're familiar with it.
Now to help you with this you can
actually answer this series of questions
to help you transform your concepts into
an objective set of rules. So let me go
through with them. Number one, which
markets are you trading? So this pretty
much you know it's straight
straightforward. Is it a currency pair,
stocks, futures, etc.? Next one, which
time frame are you trading? Is it the
lower time frame, the 5 minutes, 15
minutes, or my favorite, daily time
frame? How do you manage your risk such
that if the trade goes against you, you
can actually contain your losses? And
number four, what are the conditions of
your trading setup? Yeah, like like you
know, kind of like let's say you want to
find a wife. What are the conditions
that your potential partner must have?
Is it long hair, short hair, armpit
hair? I have no idea. Yeah, you decide.
Next one, when do you enter a trade?
What's the entry trigger that will get
you into a trade? Number six, where to
exit if you are wrong. For most people,
they are familiar with a stop-loss. And
that's pretty much uh one way to answer
question number six, having a stop-
loss, a price based stop-loss. And
number seven, when to exit if you are
right, aka right, take profit.
And the fourth step of the framework is
this test. Test the trading system. You
can do it either through back testing or
forward testing. Personally, my favorite
is to back test because it say saves me
a ton of time and money. And the reason
why you want to test the trading system
is because you want to validate it that
it works before risking a single cent.
Make sense? Why would you want to trade
something that you do not know whether
it works or not in the live markets
using real money? Because that's just
taking on additional risk. And also when
you test the trading system, you get to
identify the strength and weakness of
the system. You'll know when it does
well and when it underperforms and you
can better manage your expectations. And
when you do that, guess what? You're
going to build confidence in your
trading system because you know how it
has performed historically. You know
what market conditions it tends to do
well and what market conditions it tends
to underperform. So your expectations
are in check and this allows you to
trade the system with confidence for
years to come. Agree? If you agree,
smash the thumbs up button, right? And
subscribe to the channel. And of course,
when you test the system, when you back
test, you get faster feedback loop so
you can quickly improve. You can see,
you know, what's not working, what
doesn't work so well. The feedback loop,
the iterations is much faster. So you
can quickly improve on things. This is
kind of like buying a car. You want to
test the car, go for a test drive before
you buy it because you don't want to buy
a lemon. So, same thing for trading
strategy. You want to test it first,
back test it first to make sure that
yep, it's working within your
expectations before you risk real money
in the markets. Okay. So now next moving
on I'm going to walk you through an
example a full-fledged example of this
four-step framework to show you how I
use this to create profitable trading
strategies.
So in this section right I'm going to
share with you how I go about developing
one of such strategy which is a futures
trend following system so you can profit
in bull and bare markets even during a
recession. I will give you the complete
trading rules, even walk you through a
few chart examples so you can see how it
works plus give you the back tested
results. So hopefully it inspires
confidence in you or you can use this as
a framework, a foundation to you know
start building something of your own. So
let's get to it.
So firstly read books with back tested
results. So this is a book I read
following the trend by Andreas Cleno. A
fantastic book especially for those of
you who wants to get involved in futures
trend following.
Next, I extract the essence behind trend
following. So, after reading the book,
it really boils down to this few simple
concepts. Number one, trade in the
direction of the trend. This means you
want to be buying breakouts and to short
breakdowns. And of course, buying
breakouts isn't the only way. You can
also use things like moving average,
moving average crossover to get you into
a trade and to exit the trade. Number
two, you want to trail your stop loss so
you can write the trend. This means you
don't want to have a fixed target profit
because when you have a fixed target
profit, you are kind of limiting your
upside. You're capping your profit
potential. So this is why as trend
follower, you never have a fixed target
profit. You always trail your stop- loss
so you can write the trend up higher.
And number three, you want to trade as
many markets as possible across
different sectors to increase your odds
of capturing a trend. This means you
don't want to be just trading, let's
say, currency pairs because currency
pairs, how many are there? there's like
maybe 20 30 at most and the rest are
pretty much or rather they all generally
correlated to one another. So this is
why you want to trade currency pairs,
bonds, indices, commodities, orange
juice, metal, etc. to increase your odds
of capturing the trends out there
because you're trading across so many
different sectors and you want to keep
your losses small. So this way when you
catch a trend, when you catch one
winning trade, it's enough to pay for
many of these small losses and still put
you in the green. In essence, right,
this is the key concepts behind futures
trend following. Moving on to the third
step of the framework. Do you remember
what it is?
No. Yeah. Memory of a goldfish. Yeah.
Third step is this. turn it into an
objective set of rules and I've given
you this list of seven questions. If you
can answer all of these seven questions,
then guess what? You would have a
complete trading system and that's a
huge step forward. So now let's answer
each of these questions. So we have a
complete trend following system. So
let's talk about the markets. So these
are the markets that we are trading. As
you can see, I'm trading across
different sectors, you know, currencies,
metals, commodities, bonds, etc. It's
not a full-fledged sectors, but this
gives us enough diversification for this
current trading video purposes. The time
frame is the daily time frame and our
risk management is 2% risk on each
trade. So, this means if a trade hits
our stop- loss, our trailing stop-loss
or rather our initial trailing
stop-loss, we will lose not more than 2%
of our account.
Now, here comes the most exciting part,
the trading rules. Ready? Let's go.
Don't blink.
Okay, there you have it. Pretty simple
stuff. So if the trading rules for long
is this, if the price, right, the market
that we are trading, if the price closes
at the highest over the last 200 days,
go long. In other words, the highest
closing price over the last 200 days,
if the market did that, go long. And if
you are long, you just have a 68R
trailing stop-loss. And often one of the
common questions I get is, you know,
which is the look back period is a 20
period ATR. Okay? Okay, so in case
you're wondering, it's a 20 period ATR
and we use uh multiple of six as our
trailing stop loss. I'll share with you
some examples later on so you can see
how it looks like on the chart and how
you can write long-term trends because
your trailing stop loss will progress
progressively move up higher as the
price moves in your favor. And for
the rules for short is just the
opposite. If the price closes at the
lowest over the last 200 days, go short.
In other words, if there's a lowest
close over the last 200 days, you go
short. And if you are short, then you
just have a 6 ATR trailing stop-loss.
And that's it. That's the rules of this
trading system, right? Simple stuff.
Okay. Now, let's have a look at an
example. So, you can see this in action.
And to do this, I need a couple of
indicators to make my life easier. If
not, I I have to be counting the last
200 candles and see which is the highest
close. The first one is the Donian
channel. There's a slight modification
to this because I got the Donian channel
to just simply demarket the closing
price instead of the the highest price
or the lowest price, right? So, I used
the modify the code and get the closing
price only. I think you should be able
to find it on Trading View. It's a free
indicator. So, if not, you can just, you
know, use chat GPT or CL or whatever to
help you, you know, come up with the
script and not too difficult. So you can
see over here this is the donen channel
and what I'm looking for is for this to
touch this blue line right for it to
close beyond that level because when it
does it means that this market which is
gold has just formed the highest close
over the last 200 days and I'm going to
tell you up front this is a cherry pig
chart and I can guarantee you the next
candle is going to boom hit the highest
close over the last 200 days so at this
point now the entry trigger the setup is
And so what I need to do is to since
it's a daily time frame, I need to enter
my trade on the next day. So wait for
the next day market to open. Boom. It
opened here. Let me just highlight this
part. It opened. Okay, let me just zoom
in a little bit. Right, for those of you
who are like me getting on the getting
on my ears, right? Can't see properly.
This is the opening price. This is where
you would have gotten long on the trade
at the open of the next day. So now,
where do you then set your stop loss?
Your trailing stop loss. So remember we
have a 6 ATR trailing stop loss. You can
use this indicator over here. This one
it's called the uh chandelier exit. Uh I
think this one is from pip charlie if I
if I recall. Then this is the settings I
use 6 ATR and then the 20 period look uh
ATR. Okay. Click okay. And what's going
to happen is that this light blue line
will pop up. So this is our trailing
stop loss because from
here all the way down to here is pretty
much 6 a TR. Okay. So what we're going
to do, okay, is to
hold this position until the price until
the price reverse down and then closes
below this 68R trailing stop-loss. If it
doesn't do that, we'll be holding this
position, right? Till that happens. So
let's see what happens. And of course,
this is a cherry picked trade. So you
can see that the market of gold did
progressively move in our favor. Still
has not hit our trailing stop-loss. And
one thing about trailing stop- loss you
need to be aware of is that you can see
it progressively move up higher as the
market goes up higher along the way. So
in other words, it's kind of like
locking your profits, but still at the
same time giving it some buffer or quite
a bit of buffer, a bit of quite a bit of
wiggle room for the trade to move so you
don't get stopped out prematurely.
Okay. Okay, so you can see over here,
boom. Right, trailing stop loss still
intact,
still going up.
And finally over here, boom. Okay, I
jumped the gun a little bit too early,
but you can see over here, this candle
over here, it closed
or rather this uh this candle over here.
Okay, it closed below our 680R trailing
stop loss. Let me just highlight to you.
this candle over here, it closed below
our 68 TR trailing stop loss and this is
where we need to exit the trade. So we
exit at the next day open over here and
you know it was clearly a winning trade
because we have you know right the meat
of the move. You can see over here I
just zoom out a little bit.
Okay we enter over here as you can see
we have right the meat of the move which
is all the way here
right from here all the way until here.
And the thing about trend following is
that there are times where you get
stopped out only having to re-enter
shortly again. So you can see in this
case shortly afterwards
yeah this candle boom the price forms
another highest close over the last 200
days. So we should have again following
the rules of this system we should enter
long on the next candle which is this
over here and then this is our 6 ATR
trailing stop loss and again the same
process repeats itself again we hold
that position until we get stopped out
and in this case I think uh kind of
still still riding it as at this current
point in time as I'm shooting this video
now since the rules of this trading
system is is fixed it's objective
there's no guesswork You can back test
it and see how it has performed over
time. So let's do that. And you can see
over here I've run a back test from 2000
till I think this was 2024. You can see
that this equity curve overall it's
sloping higher over time. It's not going
up in one straight line. There is you
know pullback along the way. So over
here we have a pullback a pullback
pullback pullback. So it's important of
course to ask yourself
what lead to the pullback because that's
probably market conditions that are not
favorable for this particular trading
system and it's of course when the
market is uh choppy rangebound that's
where where you get uh such pullbacks in
your equity curve. So breaking this down
even further further you can see that in
2000 up 22%. 2008 this system is up 65%.
2020 this is uh COVID up 8%. 2022 Russia
Ukraine war up 56%. So these are the
these are the key I would say crisis
difficult periods
and you can see that this system clearly
right does well in such difficult times
as explained earlier the logic behind it
is because there's fear in the market
because of the hurt mentality this
system will usually shine and like all
trading system it doesn't make money
every month or every year so for example
you have losing months like this is 2000
March lost money 2000 May June you lose
money losing years in 200
9. As you can see over here, we have
losing years in 2012, 2013. So, but all
in all, you can see that this is a
long-term profitable trading system. And
looking even into more granular details,
you can see the total return since 2000
is about 200 2,864%,
an average of about 14% return a year.
45% winning rate. This means that you
actually lose more than half the time.
Your payoff ratio is 1.74. How this is
being calculated is just take your
average size of your profits divided by
the average size of your loss and you
get a payoff ratio. So in other words,
you can see that on average your winners
is 1.74 times larger than the size of
your average losers and maximum draw
down of 37%.
And that's not all because you can also
tweak the trading system. So after the
testing phase, if you are happy, you
want to trade live with it, right, feel
free to start with a small account. But
if you still want to fine-tune things
and make things better, then of course
there are many things that you can
tweak. Number one, you can tweak the
length of the breakout. Maybe instead of
looking for the highest close over the
last 200 days, maybe that is too
long-term for you, you can go with a
50-day breakout, 100 days, whatever. Do
the testing and see what it says.
You can also change the duration of the
trend, the type of trends that you're
riding. Maybe 6 ATR is too long-term for
you. You want to shorten it, right? 3
ATR, that's fine. Or if you don't want
to use a ATR to trail your stop loss,
you can use a moving average. There are
different ways to go about doing it. So,
this is where you can have different
types of entries and exits. If you don't
want to trade breakouts, you can also
trade moving average crossover like what
I talked about earlier. And of course
you can add more markets, more markets
like indices, more currency pairs, more
commodities, you know, it's endless. And
with this in mind, you can take one
simple strategy, the trend following
strategy, and create multiple trading
systems based on this strategy. Maybe
one is a long-term trend following
system, one is a short-term trend
following system. You know, really, it's
it's the ideas are limitless. And I
leave it to you because this is where
you have to do the work on your own. And
once you've done back testing, right,
you will realize that trend following
has its pros and cons. Number one,
there's no correlation to the stock
market. So whether the market is up or
down, trend following the results won't
have much resemblance to it. Usually
does well in a bare market, in a crisis,
as I've explained why earlier. If not,
rewind this video, watch it from the
start because everything is built on
chronological order.
The downside of this system is that low
winning rate. You've seen that you win
about 40 to 45% of the time. And it can
be difficult for most traders psychology
because you have to endure draw down.
Your draw down can be months or
sometimes even years. Imagine trading a
system only to see it lose you know for
one year, two years. It's
psychologically difficult for most
traders. So this is why I'm a huge
proponent right of having multiple
trading systems, multiple strategies.
You can have a trend following strategy.
You can have a mean reversion one, etc.
And this helps smooth out and improve
your risk adjusted returns over time.
Now, as a recap to what you've just
learned today, you have learned what I
call the RAT formula. No, I'm not I'm
not calling you a rat, but it's called
the RAT formula. So, this stands for
read trading books that contains trading
systems and back tested results. Number
two, extract the essence behind the
strategy, the concepts that make it
work, the logic behind it to why it
should work. Then turn it into an
objective set of rules. I shared with
you seven questions that will help you
take any trading concepts and to turn it
into a complete trading system. And of
course, you want to test it, back test
it, forward test the trading system to
see whether it works or not. And to take
things a step further, you can also
tweak the trading system. You can use
one strategy and turn it into multiple
trading systems based on that one
strategy. That's definitely possible as
well. And before you go again, if you
want to get my list of top trading
books, the books that I've read that I
realized that contains complete trading
system with back tested results, then
just I'll put the link in the tell you
what in the description below. Just
click on this link. You'll be brought to
this page. Enter your email and I'll
send you my list of top trading books.
trading books that I've read that
contains complete trading system with
back tested results. So this way you
don't have to start from scratch and
it's going to save you a ton of time,
effort and money. So with that said, I
wish you good luck, good trading,
pleasure speaking with you again and I
will talk to you soon.